Guide to the Photograph File of Close Up Magazine
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Photograph File of Close Up Magazine
1911-1947
1926-1933
YCAL MSS 337
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.98
(3 boxes)
This collection consists chiefly of promotional photographs and film stills created by motion picture studios for their films and actors, which the editors of Close Up used to illustrate the magazine.
Macpherson, Kenneth
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was formerly the possession of Islay Lyons (born 1922), photographer and longtime companion of Kenneth Macpherson.
Purchased from Elysium Press on the Elizabeth Wakeman Dwight Memorial Fund, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Kenneth Macpherson (1903-1971) and
Kenneth Macpherson was a novelist and photographer with an interest in film making. In 1927, he married Annie Winifred Ellerman (1894-1983), also known as Bryher. With their partner, Hilda Doolittle (1886-1961), also known as H.D., they established the POOL Group, a partnership that produced publications and films. The trio also established and edited Close Up (1927-1933), an influential magazine focused on intellectual discussions of cinema. In 1931, the editorial board included Henry Joseph Hasslacher (1907-1985), also known as Oswell Blakeston. Apart from the editors, contributors to Close Up included poet Robert Herring, film critic Harry A. Potamkin, the novelist Dorothy Richardson, and psychoanalyst Hanns Sachs.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists chiefly of promotional photographs and film stills created by motion picture studios for their films and actors, which the editors of Close Up used to illustrate the magazine. The photographs document both popular and avant-garde cinema, as well as the transition period from silent films to films with sound. The Universum Film AG motion picture studio in Germany distributed most of the photographs in the collection, while other photographs came from companies in the Soviet Union, United States, Great Britain, France, and Japan. Many of the photographs have layout notes on their versos by the editors related to their publication in Close Up. Ink stamps or affixed labels on the versos of many of the photographs identify the films and actors. Several photographs have autographs, most notably an inscription by Sergei Eisenstein (1898-1948) to Macpherson. A significant group of photographs documents Borderline (1930), an experimental silent film by Kenneth MacPherson and the POOL Group, which starred Paul Robeson (1898-1976) and explored intersections of racial values. Other large groups of photographs also document Die Liebe der Jeanne Ney (1927), directed by Georg Wilhelm Pabst (1885-1967), and ¡Qué viva México!, directed by Eisenstein. A group of photographs unrelated to Close Up magazine documents the film, Dreams That Money Can Buy (1947), co-produced by Macpherson with its director, Hans Richter (1888-1976).
Each folder in the collection contains a single photographic print, except where two or more photographic prints are noted.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Films, 1911-1947. II. Actors and Other Subjects, circa 1925-1947 November 13.
Experimental films -- Pictorial works; Motion pictures -- Pictorial works; Photographic prints; Blakeston, Oswell; H. D. (Hilda Doolittle), 1886-1961; Bryher, 1894-1983; Eisenstein, Sergei, 1898-1948; Macpherson, Kenneth; Pabst, G. W. (Georg Wilhelm), 1885-1967; Richter, Hans, 1888-1976; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976 -- Pictorial works; UFA (Firm) -- Pictorial works
- Films, 1911-1947; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by the name of the film in its original language, and when appropriate, parenthetical English or alternative titles.
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of film stills and promotional photographs and film stills created by motion picture studios to promote their films. The most substantive material relates to several the films, including Borderline, Dreams That Money Can Buy, The Love of Jeanne Ney, and ¡Qué viva México!
  - Die 3 Groschen-Oper (The Threepenny Opera), 1931; 6 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adieu Mascotte (Goodbye, Mascotte), 1929; 3 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Asphalt, 1929; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Blackmail, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Der Blaue Engel (The Blue Angel), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Die Blonde Nachtigall (Blonde Nightingale), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Blonde Venus, 1932; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Borderline, 1930; 16 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Die Büchse der Pandora (Pandora's Box), 1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Der Bund der Drei (The League of Three), 1929; 5 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chez Les Mangeurs D'Hommes (Land of the Cannibals), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Congress Dances, 1931; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - A Cottage on Dartmoor, 1929; 4 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chushingura (The Vengeance Of The Forty-Seven Ronin), 1932; 3 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dolly Macht Karriere (Dolly Gets Ahead or Dolly's Way to Stardom), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Don Quixote, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dreams That Money Can Buy, 1947; 12 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Die Drei von der Tankstelle (Three Good Friends, or Three from the Gasoline Station), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Drifters, 1929; 3 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Duck Soup, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Einbrecher (Murder for Sale), 1930; 6 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Emperor Jones, 1933; 4 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Das Flötenkonzert von Sans-souci (The Flute Concert of Sans-Souci), 1930; 9 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Four Feathers, 1929; 4 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Frozen Fate, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ginrei Fuji Ni Yomigaeru (Three Crews and One Girl, or Mount Fuji Covered With Snow), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Greek Street, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Hallelujah!, 1929; 6 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Hearts in Dixie, 1929; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Hibari (Skylark), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hochverrat (High Treason), 1929; 5 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hokuspokus (Hocus-pocus), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Hurrah! Ich lebe! (Hurrah! I'm Alive!, or The False Widow), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - I'm No Angel, 1933; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - In the Days of Chivalry, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Jakon Mado (Way of Evil: Part I), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Kagaribi (The Torch), 1928; 5 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Kaijin (Ashes), 1929 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Kare to Den'en (He and the Countryside), 1928; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Koban Shigure (Shower of Coins), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Koi no jazz (Love and Jazz), 1929 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Kurokami yasha (Black Hair Demon), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Kurueru Nìngyoshi (Insane Doll Maker), 1926; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - L'Argent (Money), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - L'Horloge Magique (The Magic Clock), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Der Letzte Walzer (The Last Waltz), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Die Liebe der Jeanne Ney (The Love of Jeanne Ney), 1927; 15 photographic prints and 3 magazine clippings (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - The Letter, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Liebeswalzer (The Love Waltz), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Little People Burlesques, 1930; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Manolescu - Der König der Hochstapler (Manolescu - The King of the Swindlers), 1929; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Der Meister von Nürnberg (The Master of Nuremberg), 1927 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Melodie des Herzens (Melody of the Heart), 1929; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Monte Carlo Madness, 1932; 11 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Nani Ga Kanojo Wo Sosasetaka? (What Made Her Do It?), 1930; 4 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - The Night Patrol, 1926; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Novyy Vavilon (The New Babylon), 1929 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Nuits de Princes (Night of the Princes), 1929; 2 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Oatsurae Jirokichigoshi (Jirokichi, The Ratkid), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Ogasawara Ikinokami (Where Are The Dreams Of Youth?), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - La P'tite Lili (The Little Lili), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Le Petit Chaperon Rouge (Little Red Riding Hood), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - The Power and the Glory, 1933; 4 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Princesse, à Vos Ordres! (Her Highness Commands!), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Putyovka v Zhizn (Road to Life), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - ¡Qué Viva México!, 1932; 28 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 66-68)
  - Rag Fair, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Ranto no Chimata (Battle in the Streets of Kyoto, or Street Brawl), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Reimei Izen (Before Dawn), 1931; 4 photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Rosenmontag (Rose Monday), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Le Sang d'un Poète (The Blood of a Poet), 1930; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - The Scarlet Empress, 1934; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Die Schmugglerbraut von Mallorca (The Girl from Valencia), 1929; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Schuldig (Guilty), 1928; 3 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Shinel (The Cloak), 1926 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Der Sieger (The Victor, or The Winner), 1932; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Die Singende Stadt (The Singing City), 1930 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - The Sold Appetite, 1928; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - The Song of Songs, 1933; 10 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Spartakiada, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Spione (Spies), 1928; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Der Sträfling aus Stambul (The Felon from Istanbul), 1929; 3 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Stampede (Africa in Flames), 1929; 3 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Staroye i Novoye (Old and New, or The General Line), 1929 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Tabu, a Story of the South Seas, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - The Temporary Widow, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Tiere Sehen Dich An! (Animals Looking at You!), 1929; 6 photographic prints (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Der Tiger (The Tiger Murder Case), 1930; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Uncle Tom's Cabin, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Under the Southern Cross, 1927; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Une Idylle à la Plage (Idyll at the Beach), 1931 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Unmei No Ko (Child of Destiny or Capital Punishment), 1926 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Unmögliche Liebe (Crown of Thorns), 1932; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Der Unsterbliche Lump (The Immortal Vagabond), 1930 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Varieté (Jealousy, or Passions of Men), 1925 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Vesnoy (Springtime), 1929; 4 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Die Weiße Hölle Vom Piz Palü (The White Hell of Pitz Palu), 1929 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Der Weiße Teufel (The White Devil), 1930; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Wenn du Einmal Dein Herz Verschenkst (The Equator Tramp), 1930 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Die Wunderbare Lüge der Nina Petrowna (The Wonderful Lies of Nina Petrovna), 1929 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Yowamushi (The Coward), 1927; 3 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Zolotoy Klyuv (A Golden Beak), 1929 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Zwei Herzen und ein Schlag (Two Hearts Beat as One), 1932 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Unidentified films, circa 1915-1935; 27 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 106)
- Actors and Other Subjects, circa 1925-1947 November 13; Series II
  Arranged alphabetically. Group photographs are filed under the surname of the first person on the left of the image. A small group of photographs that document miscellaneous subjects are filed at the end.
  The series primarily consists of promotional photographs created by motion picture studios for actors they employed, as well as a small group of photographs that document other subjects, consisting of a vehicle used by Universum Film AG, plans for Rockefeller Center, photographic portraits by Helmar Leski, and postcards for zoos in Switzerland.
  - Annabella (1907-1996), 1933 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Albach-Retty, Wolf (1906-1967), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Bando, Tsumasaburo (1901-1953), circa 1930; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Bársony, Rózsi (1909-1977), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - Benfer, Friedrich (1905-1996) and Jenny Jugo (1904-2001), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - De Liguoro, Rina (1892-1966), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Dietrich, Marlene (1901-1992), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Eisenstein, Sergei (1898-1948), 1928 July (Box 3, Folder 114)
    With an inscription on the recto of the mount to Macpherson.
  - Fanck, Arnold (1889-1974), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Fritsch, Willy (1901-1973), circa 1930; 3 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Fröhlich, Gustav (1902-1987), circa 1930; 3 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - Harbou, Thea von (1888-1954), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Harvey, Lilian (1906-1968), circa 1930; 6 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Harvey, Lilian, and Wilhelm Thiele (1890-1975), circa 1929-1932 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Harvey, Lilian, Willy Fritsch, Leni Riefenstahl (1902-2003), Camilla Horn (1903-1996) and Christa Tordy (1902-1945), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Junghans, Wolfram, and Paul Krien (born 1873), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Loos, Theodor (1883-1954), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - Lucien, Modest, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - Magarill, Sofiya (1900-1943), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Maris, Mona (1903-1991), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - Maritza, Sari (1910-1987), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - Masaryk, Tomáš Garrigue (1850-1937), circa 1930; 3 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - Morena, Erna (1885-1962), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - Nagy, Käthe von (1904-1973), circa 1930; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Narlian, Albert Percy Michael (1879-1959), 1947 November 13 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - Nielsen, Asta (1881-1972), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 132)
  - Schünzel, Reinhold (1886-1954), circa 1930; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 133)
  - Shiga, Seiro, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 134)
  - Tolstoy, Ilya (1866-1933) and Michael Curtiz (1886-1962), circa 1927 (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - Tschechowa, Olga (1897-1980), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 136)
  - Ichimura Uzaemon XV (1874-1945), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 137)
  - Uzaemon, Ichimura, XV, and Onoe Kikugoro VI (1885-1949), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 138)
  - Uzaemon, Ichimura, XV, Onoe Kikugoro VI, and Kichiemon Nakamura (1886-1954), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 139)
  - Van Aalten, Truus (1910-1999), circa 1925 (Box 2, Folder 140)
  - Vernon, Suzy (1901-1997), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 141)
  - Waschneck, Erich (1887-1970), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 142)
  - Weyher, Ruth (1901-1983), circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 143)
  - Mercedes-Benz automobile with a camera on its roof used by Universum Film AG for its Ufatone-Weekly films, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 144)
  - Copy photograph of a preliminary drawing for Rockefeller Center, New York, New York, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 145)
  - Unidentified woman and man photographed by Helmar Lerski (1871-1956) from Köpfe des Alltags: Unbekannte Menschen Gesehen (1931), 2 photographic prints (Box 3, Folder 146)
  - Photographic postcards of animals at the Zoologischer Gartens in Zurich and Basel, Switzerland, circa 1930; 3 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 147)